So, in this video I would like to
develop once with you an example Petri net.
In this program, in this app, which
is also linked in the Moodle course.
On the one hand, I would like to
do this in order to talk through a somewhat
clearer example with you.
In the lecture slides, up to now,
you've only seen completely artificial Petri nets.
So here it will
be about really modeling something.
On the other hand, I
want to show you this tool.
I also want to show you how to use it.
So that you can see it in action, how
you can use it in practice,
for example, or to explore models.
So that you can not only draw the
things here (which is of course nice, also
for your practice tasks maybe), but that
you can also execute the Petri nets.
So for example you can see the
firing, which I had just done
manually on my whiteboard last week.
The program can do that automatically.
Then you can play
around with your Petri nets.
So that's all what I want
to teach you with the example here.
The example itself is one that I
came up with two, three, four years
ago and now actually use every year.
Because I couldn't think of anything else at the
time, but it turned out that this example is
quite nice, because it's still small,
but it models a concrete illustrative situation.
And above all, there
are also various features in
it that are interesting
for the exercises, for example.
So here are resources
used; how to express certain
conditions that you have in your
head well in a Petri net; etc.
Although this is a small example,
there are some interesting features in it.
Namely, I had thought at
the time, I'm going to model
my son's afternoon schedule.
This also means that the example
will be a little different each year,
depending on what my son's
plans are at the moment.
Whether he just has to
do a dance class from
school, or just does
his regular sports, or whatever.
This year, anyway, I'm really only able
to model the afternoon from
last year because right now, with
the pandemic, there are new
regulations coming up every week anyway.
And for example there is no training at
all or even school is not taking place.
But it's just an example.
You shouldn't really believe that my
family are such freaks that we
organize our everyday
life with Petri nets.
And actually, my son will be of
full age the year after next and then
it would be absurd to
go on like this anyway. :-)
Anyway, it's just an example.
Let's imagine that I would like to
model what a typical afternoon looks like.
For this I certainly
need places and transitions.
And I could think, for example, that
there are at least two at transitions (at
things that happen;
actions that are executed).
You can see here that I
can place things on my workspace.
So places, that's these circles here.
And you can also see
already, there are two types of
transitions: these filled
and the unfilled.
In the slides earlier, I
mostly drew the transitions just like
this: just using unfilled boxes.
In this program, though, you would
have to take these filled-in rectangles.
Because this other kind of transitions
in the program is not exactly the
one we know and need from the lecture.
So if you work with the program here, you
would have to take
these filled rectangles as transitions.
Then you can edit the transitions.
So for example, you
can change the orientation.
Let's say I would like
to draw it like this.
Then I can do it like this.
And I can give names
to the transitions and places.
So we can also directly
think about what I want here.
What I would like
for the two transitions:
One is to be the homework
that my son has to do.
And on the other hand, he goes to training, so
he does sports, and that should also be an action.
Maybe I actually
name the transitions first.
So for example here the "doing homework"
and this other transition would be the "exercising".
Then we already know, in order
for such a transition to be
executed, usually you would
need resources for it somehow.
So it's certainly not a coincidence
that I've already provided two places here
where I still want
to put tokens afterwards.
So you could imagine that there
is just this one place here
where the set homework is.
That can be also several
on the day, the set homework.
And then these would probably
be the completed tasks down here.
And you could imagine that the action of
doing homework turns set
homework into done homework.
And that is exactly when
I create connections in between.
As you can see, the tool
always adds a one to the connections.
This corresponds to the representation that
I had on the slides, that
there would be nothing
at all at the arrow.
I had said that you
can have numbers on it.
That corresponds to the
weighting of such an edge.
And I had said:
If there is nothing on
it, then we implicitly mean 1.
In fact, in the tool,
the 1 is always written down.
And over here you could just ask:
What are the meanings of the places here?
Here it's about the
training that's coming up,
and for example here the post place might
be that my son is back from training.
Now you can also draw connections here,
and then you can consider that while there's
probably only training once a day, there
might be several homework assignments to do.
And that would be expressed by having
different numbers of tokens on these spots.
Up here with this green plus,
you can add tokens to places.
So maybe there's three homeworks
a day and one time training.
And then this could be my
first Petri net expressing this fact.
What can I do with
it now, with this Petri net?
I can execute it.
So, of course, I can look at
it with our intuition from the lecture
and say that I could, for example, execute
this transition because there is a token here.
There are even three lying there.
If I were to execute the transition once,
a token would disappear from
above and end up down here.
And I can actually do that.
I can go to animation mode here, and then
we'll see an animation history here
on the left, for one thing.
First of all, the start marking.
That's the one that I painted.
And then we see here in red now
those transitions that
are currently activated.
That's both of them at the beginning.
Then I can
actually execute transitions here.
I can say: I click on
this, I want to execute this.
Then a) what has happened
is recorded here on the left,
and b) the transition has just been
executed and a token has moved down here.
Then I can execute further transitions.
And here we also see that
after I've executed the train once,
this transition is no
longer activated, no longer red.
That means I can only continue to fire
here and then I would have executed the
petri net once completely and
no further actions would be possible.
And here on the left I
would see what the execution history was:
Do homework, train,
do homework, do homework.
What's also interesting here:
You can also, instead of clicking
through yourself, tell the system to
just execute any
sequence of enabled transitions.
I can say "randomly
fire a transition" up here.
And then the system would take
the right one, for example, and
I would see a
possible execution sequence here.
Then, without clicking through
myself, I could simply
try it out several times and see:
Do we get sequences here that make sense?
If this is not the case, then
perhaps I have made a modeling error.
In this simple case, of course,
there is not much going on.
There are some possible sequences here that
always consist of: do tasks three times,
train once, in any order.
Because, if we're in the
language of parallelism and concurrency, these
are completely independent
blocks of action.
So they're not linked
in any way, therefore concurrent,
and any order would be possible.
Now that was still very trivial.
Now one could consider:
How could we make the model more interesting,
for example, to represent several days as well?
First of all, one could say:
These blocks do not
have to be completely independent.
One could also imagine that there are
not simply three tokens here at the
beginning and one token here, but
that these places must first be filled.
There is a start of the
day or the afternoon, and then
the tasks are set
and the training is prepared.
And not simple:
There are already tokens lying there.
How could this
be organized or represented?
For example, you could have
a source like this here.
So a transitions, which is
to be fired at the beginning.
What could it be called?
It could be called
"coming out of school".
The action that starts the afternoon.
My son is coming out of school.
And I'm going to take the tokens back
down from these places and instead make sure that
when the action "coming out of school"
is executed, then these two places are filled.
And the right place actually with
a token through that 1, and on
the left arrow I'd like
to have the weight three.
So that would be equivalent to what we had
earlier, which is that three homeworks would be set directly.
Now the model would look like this.
So at the beginning
nothing is assigned at
all, but there is a
transition that has no preconditions.
That is, it can fire directly.
And if I fire it, then
the three tokens would land here,
one token would land here, and
then I could simulate processes like before.
Now we can simulate several days.
We can say:
Come back from school,
train, homework, homework, homework, come
back from school, do
more homework, train again, ...
Different sequences are possible.
Now you can also determine, if I model
it this way, something is awkward or strange.
Because it would also be possible
here, since there are no preconditions for
this transition, that simply coming out
of school again and again, so
to speak, without ever
doing homework or training.
That is certainly
not a sensible sequence.
We also see that a
lot of homework then accumulates
here without ever being done.
That's because of my modeling, which
is a little bit awkward at
the moment, that I just have this
transition up here with no precondition at all.
That would have to be fixed.
Maybe you could say:
There is one more place.
Let it just be called "Start",
for example, and it contains one token.
And this one token is a
precondition for getting out of school.
That's how I imagine it.
That is, once this action "coming out
of school" would be able to be executed.
After that, the homework would be
occupied and the training would be prepared.
So, let's try this out.
If I proceed like this, I could
"come from school" here at the beginning,
and then do any
order of homework and training.
And it can't happen, like just
now, coming out of school several times.
Because it is possible exactly
once here at the beginning.
Then what else could I
imagine that belongs to an afternoon?
Maybe it is mean that
you can only do homework
and have no - besides sports
- other leisure activities or opportunities.
For example, my
son would actually naturally
spend part of the afternoon playing.
So there may still be both
an action and resources for that.
The action would be "playing", and
that would be playing with the Playstation.
Therefore there has to be a token on
it, so that this action can then be executed.
The play action has no postcondition.
Playing is not productive, so to speak.
Nothing comes out of it.
While with the "doing homework"
just completed tasks come out.
With playing nothing more comes out.
Then you could also imagine
that it might be quite nice
that you can play not
only once, but that (especially after
doing homework) you
can play several times.
Now that would make it so that
when homework was done, a) the homework
was done, and b) there would
be other tokens here on this Playstation
site that would allow you to
play more often than just exactly once.
I wanted to introduce that.
And then I had another idea.
In the execution just now there was a
start and at some point it was over.
But it would certainly also make
sense to perhaps also explicitly record this
conclusion of the day/afternoon as an
action in the execution log (which
was always created on the left
when I ran a simulation like this).
There must be a transition for this.
It must have a meaningful name, and it
would be executed at the end of the day.
So it could be called: "Day's work done".
And when is the day's work done?
Well, when the homework is
done and the training is finished.
And the day's work is only really done
when all three homework tasks have been done,
which have been created up here (you
can still see the 3 up there).
So we expect these three homeworks to
be done, then there are three tokens here.
And only when that's the
case, it should be possible to
execute this transition
that ends the afternoon.
Okay, that would be
my current modeling status now.
And then we can take another look
at what actions are possible as a result.
Whether we already have a
model that somehow captures all intentions.
But we can already see
directly that there is something strange
here when we look
at the activated transitions.
That here the action to play
is already possible before
even coming back from school.
That is certainly awkward.
If we ignore that for the moment,
then otherwise the processes already make sense.
So coming from school, maybe
doing homework, playing once, even
being able to play again
(because homework has already been
done), then maybe going to
practice, then after practice unfortunately having
to do the more
homework, and then deciding:
Is good for today, day's work
done, or maybe also still play
and only then maybe finish the day.
So that would
be already sensible sequences.
And even if I do the random
sequences again, meaningful sequences come out (except
for this aspect, that playing could
happen before coming back from school).
How can I deal with
the problem that here unrealistically the
playing (or the afternoon) starts
before coming back from school?
That would still have
to be controlled somehow.
I could say, of course:
We'll control this by
not having this badge here.
But that would only
help on the first day.
Let's imagine that in
reality, of course, we don't
want to model just one afternoon.
And let's assume for this that
we can fill this starting point again,
namely when the day's work is done.
After a full run, the next day can begin.
If I do it this way, it won't
help me to remove this one token here.
Then it would still be like this:
Once out of school, there
would be three homework assignments
here, and when those are
done, tokens will accumulate here.
They might not all be used up that day.
And then when the day's work is
done and the next day starts, suddenly I
would be able to play
again before coming back from school.
So somehow we would still have to make
sure that this play
action doesn't just always happen.
But not only depends on
the occupancy of this place
here, but also depends on whether
we just have afternoon or not.
So whether the action "come out of
school" was carried out in advance or not.
It may not be directly at the
beginning of a new day (after the
day's work of the previous day
is done) already this play action applicable.
Now you can ask yourself:
How could this be organized?
Is it possible to prevent this?
And there is a possibility, this
is a typical modeling trick or
modeling pattern in Petri nets.
If you want to make
this execution dependent on something,
then of course you have to have
a place from which you consume a token.
Because that's the way
you constrain the execution of
a transition is: that
it depends on a precondition.
So, we'd like to have
a place here and the
meaning of it should ultimately
be that it's in the afternoon.
This passage is
supposed to somehow express
the fact that it's
afternoon right now, not morning.
So I'm going to
name those appropriately for now.
I call it "afternoon".
Of course, it must not
be occupied at the beginning.
Because before this "coming out
of school" transition has been executed,
it's not yet afternoon (so it's still
night or morning or in the school day).
But what I want to express is:
When coming out of school, then
this token is put down here.
Then we know it's now afternoon.
And I want to use that
then to be able to play.
So only when it's
afternoon, it's allowed to play.
Is it already?
Let's try it out.
Yes, when I come from school,
then it is in the afternoon,
and there is homework to be done, and it
can be trained; then we could proceed like this,
then it is also allowed to
play, because this place is occupied here.
There is a token consumed from here on the one
hand, and on the other hand, it is looked whether
it is in the afternoon at all.
The problem is:
After that you could never play again.
Although you have accumulated
tokens here, so to speak,
because you have done your homework nicely,
you are still not allowed to play again.
It can't be like that.
But what we could do is
actually let this arrow work both ways.
So to perform the action "play",
it must be in the afternoon.
So there has to be a token here.
Only when this token is
there, can play be performed.
But we do not want to destroy this token.
We can prevent this by
having an arrow in both directions.
Now this looks like a double
arrow, but in reality it's two arrows.
One from here to here,
and one from here to here.
This ensures that when this spot is occupied,
and only then, can it be played at all.
Then this token is used up,
but it's put right back down.
Now I could actually,
for example, accumulate several tokens
here, earned by doing homework.
And then I could play as
often as there are tokens here.
But also only because
it is in the afternoon.
Now when I perform this action, this
one token is consumed, but immediately put back.
While these tokens are really
consumed, but not put back.
You see, the transition remains activated as
long as the one token is here
(but it is also put back) and
as long as there are tokens here.
Now it would not
be possible to continue playing.
But not because it is not afternoon,
but because no tokens have been saved
here (which could be done
by doing homework again, for example).
This looks good.
What happens next?
Then the day's work is done.
Then a new afternoon starts.
This is awkward.
We don't really want
two tokens to accumulate here.
This afternoon token, it's really
just to represent the fact:
It's afternoon.
It's not afternoon twice
at the same time.
That's really supposed to be a
spot where there's always zero tokens or
one token, and it depends on whether it's
afternoon or whether my son is still in school.
How can we fix this?
The obvious thing is
that this same afternoon information
is consumed when the day ends.
(I'm trying to arrange this so that
it's easier to read everything. Other than
that, I'm not changing anything right now).
What would be the happening now?
Coming out of
school, then it's afternoon.
That means it can be played
as long as there are tokens here.
So it could also be
played directly, and homework done.
This leads to
more tokens accumulating here.
You don't have to use them up right away.
It could also be trained,
and the last homework is done,
and then the day is ended.
Then there can be no more playing either.
It is at night
or the next school morning.
That is, although there are still tokens
accumulated here, can not be played now.
Because has not yet returned from school.
If again from the school is returned,
then it is in the afternoon, then can
be played, can be used up here even
the saved up tokens of the previous day.
So if at the lecture was
not so often the Playstation on, this
can now be used more often the next day.
If we simply let this model
run randomly, i.e. really carry out
random executions here, then I
could perhaps negotiate with my
son whether he finds
the sequences/possibilities listed here acceptable.
Or if we have to change
some parameters, and if he thinks
he can play during school
hours (because we don't live
that far away from the school and
he could go home during break) or whatever.
There is *one* idea
of design captured here.
One can discuss based on the Petri net.
One can also look at these dynamics,
i.e. the sequences generated, and come
to an assessment based on those:
Did one model correctly what one wanted?
Or are there still changes to be made?
One can even generate long
sequences here in one fell swoop.
So you can say:
I would like to simply
see a history here on the
left, where the system
has executed about 50 steps.
Then I can still say
how fast that should go.
And then I can watch the system at work,
so to speak, and see the processing on the left.
Of course, further
refinements are possible.
You could think, for example, that maybe
this saving up of tokens is too much.
Maybe I'm a very strict father and
don't want, even if Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday
always homework was done diligently,
that then on Thursday somehow ten
times is played in one go,
because here all the tokens are accumulated.
If I wanted to prevent that,
I could still say, for example:
There is a weekly budget, and there may
be five tokens at the beginning of the
week, and if I then make
playing dependent on this, then I
could, so to speak, limit the
total number of executions of this action.
It would be absolutely
limited by this weekly budget.
And it would be limited by the
fact that it can only be played in
the afternoon, i.e. when
this position is occupied.
And it would be
limited independently of the
total weekly budget by
whether homework has been done.
Maybe this is my final decision now,
how afternoons can be arranged.
Maybe a bit strict, and as I said:
This is just
a somewhat tongue-in-cheek example.
I'm also uploading this as a file so you
can play around with it yourself in the tool.
But above all, you should
use the tool to create
your own Petri nets or to
rebuild some, to experiment with them.
Be it for exercises,
where you have to model
something, or be it also for examples from
the lecture from the slides or from the exercises,
where it is not about such
everyday modeling, but about artificial examples.
It might be easier for
you to work on some
tasks, if you don't just work with
paper, but actually build the
Petri nets and interact with them.
So perform actions, check
which sequences might be
possible, when to fire and when not, etc.
This tool is very convenient for that.